（ナルト）シカマル！　いるか？
Shikamaru, are you in here?
（シカナル）あん？　なんだよ？
What is it?
いのが　用があるって…。
Ino needs you.
何してんだ？
What are you doing?
写真の選別だよ。
選別？　なんで？
Sorting photos.
Sorting? What for?
（シホ）被災地から
集められた写真なんです。
These photos were salvaged
from the disaster area.
（シホ）大事な写真もあるだろうし→
I'm sure there are some
important photos here,
持ち主が判明するものは
返そうと思って。
so we want to return them
to the owners.
オメエも知ってる人がいたら
教えてくれよ。
Look through them and
see if you recognize anyone.
あぁ　それくらいなら
俺でも手伝えそうだな。
Sure! I can help with something like that.
と　いっても
知らない人ばっかだな…。
I don't know any of these people.
これは…。
This is...
俺　用を思い出したってばよ！
えっ？
I remembered something I've gotta do!
Huh?
あぁ…　この写真　もらってくぜ！
おい！　ナルト。
I'm taking this photo.
- Hey, Naruto!
- I'm taking this photo.
あっ！　そうだ。　チューリップって
どっかに咲いてたかな？
Oh, that's right.
Do you know if tulips are
in bloom anywhere around here?
チューリップですか？　ナルト君
ロマンチックな花が好きなんですね。
Tulips?
That's such a romantic flower, Naruto.
チューリップの花言葉って
永遠の愛なんですよ。
In flower language,
tulips mean "eternal love."
《なんか　面倒くせぇ視線が…》
I don't like that look she's giving me.
そんなら　里の東にある花畑なら
無事なんじゃないか？
I think the flower garden on
the east side of the village is still intact.
サンキューな　シカマル！
あぁ。
Thanks, Shikamaru!
Sure.
でも　アイツ　チューリップを
どうするつもりだ？
But why does he want tulips?
さぁ？
Who knows?
《永遠の愛か…》
Eternal love, huh?
((やべぇ！　降ってきたってばよ。
Shucks! It's starting to rain.
急いで帰んねえと！
Better hurry back!
ととっ…。
うわぁ！
いてぇ…。
Oww...
ギャーッ！
な　な…　なんだ？
W-What is that?
なんだよ！　岩か…。
Oh, it's a rock.
うん！？　なんだ？　これ…。
What is this?
札？
A tag?
「奇介」…　あとは　読めねえな。
Kisuke?
I can't make out the rest.
Oh no!
やべぇ！
は…　早く帰るってばよ。
I-I'd better get going.
サクラちゃん…。
Sakura...
サクラちゃん
そんな抱きつかなくって…。
S-Sakura... You're hugging me so hard.
サクラちゃん　ちょっと　重…。
Sakura... You're heavy.
ギャーッ！
な　な…　なんだよ！？　おっちゃん！
びっくりしたってばよ！！
Wh-Who are you, Mister?!
You gave me a scare!
（奇介）こっちも　びっくりしたよ！
急に　大声出すから。
I'm the one who's scared...
with you screaming out like that!
って…　おい　おっちゃん！　なんで
勝手に　人ん家に入ってんだよ！？
Hey Mister! You can't just
enter someone's home!
Huh?
うん！？　ううん…。
さぁ？　気づいたら　ここにいて…。
I don't know.
I came to, and here I was.
はぁ！？　なんだよ？　気づいたら
ここって　そんなバカな話…。
Huh?
What do you mean you "came to"?
That's ridiculous.
出た！！　オバケ！
（奇介）なに！？　どこ？　どこ？
A ghost!
What?! Where?!
どこにもいないじゃないか。
心臓に悪いだろ！
There's nothing there!
You're gonna give me
a heart attack!
おっちゃん…　それって…。
Mister... T-Take a look.
うん？
Huh?
そんな落ち込むなってばよぉ…。
Don't get too depressed.
つっても　無理か。
I guess it's hard not to.
なあ　おっちゃん。
自分が死んだの　覚えてねえの？
So, Mister, you don't remember dying?
そういえば…。
That's right!
そういえば？
What is it?
何も覚えてない。
I don't remember anything.
だあ～っ…。
Wha-?
っていうか
自分の名前も何も覚えてない。
In fact, I don't even remember
my name.
記憶喪失のオバケなんて
んなの聞いたことねえぞ！
I've never heard of a ghost
with amnesia!
俺もだよ。
君　何か　俺に祟られることした？
Same here.
Did you do something that
would make me haunt you?
んなことするわけねえってばよ！
Why would I?!
俺は　おっちゃんなんて
全然　知らねえし→
I don't even know you!
祟られるようなことなんか
ちっと…。
Why would I have
done something to you?!
あっ！
どうした？
- Wait!
- What?
Come to think of it,
last night...
そういえば　夕方…。
"Kisuke"
Back there in the hills
I peeled off a weird tag.
裏山で
変なお札を剥がしたなぁ。
お札？
ああ　ちょっと待って。
A tag?
Hold it!
それで　俺　化けて出てるの？
And that turned me into a ghost?
これだってばよ。
This is it!
奇介…　奇介ってのか？　俺。
Kisuke? Am I Kisuke?
そもそも　奇介とは名前なのか？
だとしたら　どこの奇介か？
Okay then, I guess Kisuke is my name.
But where am I from?
そんなの知らねえってばよ。
そうだよな…。
How would I know?
You're right.
でも　死んだんなら
俺　なんで成仏できないんだ？
But if I'm dead, why can't I just
rest in peace?
あっ！　この世に
なんか未練があるから→
I heard that ghosts remain in
the real world
成仏できねえって
聞いたことあるぞ。
because they have
lingering attachments.
未練？　未練か…。
Lingering... attachments, huh?
何の未練だろう？
I wonder what kind of attachments?
《う～ん…　これ
どうしたらいいんだってばよ》
What am I supposed to do with him?
ano suiheisen ga touzakatte iku
Far beyond the horizon it continues
ao sugita sora ni wa ashita sura egake nakute
A sky so blue, you can't draw tomorrow
iki mo dekinai kurai yodonda hito no mure
It's stifling with crowds of people down here
boku wa itsukara koko ni moguri kondan da?
Just when did I dive into this?
kanashimi nante hakidashite mae dake mi tereba iin dakke?
Spit out sadness and keep looking ahead, right?
sore ja totemo matomo de irarenai
You can't stay true to yourself like that
subete o boku ga teki ni mawashite mo
Even if I turn against everything,
hikari o kasuka ni kanji terun da
I still feel glimmers of light
soko made yuke sou nara
If I could only reach it...
iki o shitakute koko wa kurushikute
I want to breathe, I'm suffocating here
yami o miageru dake no boku ja
Only looking up into the dark means,
ukabu houhou mo nai daibaa
I'm a diver who can't surface
iki o shite mite
Take a deep breath
tada no shiawase ni kizuitara mou nidoto oborenai yo
Discover joy, plain and simple and you'll never drown
- Leaf's History -
The Man Who Died Twice
((どうやら　おっちゃんが見えんの
俺だけみてぇだな。
Looks like I'm the only one
who can see you.
封印を解いた君だけに見えるのか。
So only you, who broke the seal,
can see me.
となると　君だけが頼りだな　ナルト。
That means you're the only one
I can rely on, Naruto.
ハア…　しようがねえ。
片っ端から聞いてみっか。
Then I guess I'll just have to go out
and ask around!
奇介？　知らないねぇ。
Kisuke? I don't know such a person.
聞いたことないなぁ。
Never heard of him.
知らないでちゅ。
I don't know him.
ニャーゴ。
ハア…　チェッ。
Sheesh.
誰も　おっちゃんのこと
知らねえってばよ。
No one knows you, Mister.
ダメか…。
あっ！　そうだ！
So it didn't work.
Hey, I know!
（イズモ）面会は無理だ。
三代目は　いらっしゃらない。
You can't see him.
The Third Hokage isn't in.
何かあったのか？
Did something happen?
重要な会議に出ておられる。
He's attending an important meeting.
ふ～ん
火影のじいちゃんなら→
I figured Old Man Hokage
would know something.
なんか知ってると
思ったんだけどな。
しゃあねえや。　他を当たるか。
Well then, guess I'll try someone else.
（サビル）ですから
この新たな警備網が→
With this new security network,
実現できれば　木ノ葉の防衛機能は
実に　３倍に飛躍します。
we'll be able to triple the strength
of the Hidden Leaf's defense system.
私としては　ぜひとも
この新たな防衛案に対する→
Personally, I believe this measure
is absolutely necessary,
ご理解を
皆様に求める次第であります。
and I recommend that you adopt it.
なるほどのう。
確かに　この案は名案じゃのう。
I see. Well, this is
an excellent plan indeed.
では　皆様
採決は午後ということで→
We will make the final decision
this afternoon.
休憩してください。
We'll take a recess now.
（サビル）コハル様　ホムラ様。
Lady Koharu! Lord Homura!
サビルか。
Oh, it's you, Sabiru.
（サビル）ご足労かけます。
いい案じゃった。
I appreciate your time today.
That was a good proposal.
お前も　ずいぶんと出世したな。
日頃の努力のたまものだ。
You've come up in the world.
It's a testament to your hard work.
ありがたき　お言葉。
Thank you for your kind words.
（サビル）私の生涯は
この里のためにあります。
My life is dedicated to this village.
（カカシ）あの若さで　里の新たな
防衛案を考えつくとは→
He's so young, yet he came up with
a new security plan for the village.
なかなかのものですね。
I'm very impressed.
（三代目）うむ。　午後の会議で→
If the measure is approved
during the afternoon session,
あの案が認可されれば
木ノ葉の平和は→
it will solidify the peace in
Hidden Leaf Village.
これまで以上に強固なものとなる。
やっぱ　ダメか…。
No luck.
はぁ…　俺の記憶は
戻らないのかなぁ。
Will I ever get my memory back?
そんな　しょんぼり
すんなってばよ。
Cheer up, Mister.
なっ　おっちゃん！
（サクラ）あっ　ナルト！
Hey, Naruto!
サクラちゃん！
アンタね　今日の演習　来ないで→
Sakura!
You missed today's exercises.
こんなところで
なに油売ってんのよ！
What are you dawdling around here for?!
あっ！　忘れてた！
忘れてた！　じゃないでしょ。
Oops, I completely forgot!
That's no excuse!
痛い　痛い！　いや　それが→
Oww...
No, I'm in a real pinch.
たいへんなことに
なってんだってばよ！
たいへんなこと？
ほら　この…。
A real pinch?
See! This...
Oh yeah, only I can see him.
あっ　俺以外には
見えねえんだった。
なに　わけわかんないこと
言ってんのよ！
You're not making any sense!
あんま　サボってると
先生に言いつけるわよ！
If you keep missing practice,
I'm going to tell on you to Sensei!
わかったってばよ。
ったく！
Okay, I hear you.
Jeez.
なんか　とばっちりだってばよ。
Cripes, what'd I get myself into?
すまないな　ナルト。
あっ　待ってよ　サクラちゃん！
I'm sorry, Naruto.
Hey, wait, Sakura!
なによ！
サクラちゃん　あのさ→
What?!
Do you know anyone named Kisuke
by any chance?
奇介って人　知らない？
奇介？　知らないわよ
そんな名前の人。
Kisuke?
I don't know anyone
by that name.
あっ！　そういえば
聞いたことあるかも。
Wait a second, I think I've heard
that name somewhere.
（２人）えっ！？
それって　どこで？
- What?!
- Where?!
う～ん　たしか…。
I think...
"Hidden Leaf Hospital"
((知り合いのお見舞いで
病院に行ったときに→
When I went to the hospital
to visit someone,
the patient in
the very back room...
(奥の病室に入ってた人が…))
"Kisuke Maboroshi"
あっ！
そんな…　俺じゃないか。
That's impossible.
That's me.
どうりで
成仏できねえはずだってばよ。
No wonder you can't
rest in peace, Mister.
まだ死んでねえんだもんな。
You're still alive.
(俺は　どうしてこんなとこに…))
What happened to me anyway?
((はぁ…。
おっちゃん　おっちゃん！
Mister... Mister!
ナルト。
おっちゃん家の住所
聞いてきたから→
Naruto...
I got your address,
so let's go over there.
行ってみるってばよ。
おっちゃん！
えっ？　ああ。
Mister!
Oh... okay.
ここが　俺の家。
This is my house?
チューリップ…。
A tulip.
おっちゃん家　だいぶ前に
火事になったらしい。
Your house burned down
quite a while ago.
そのとき…　言いづらいんだけど→
And I'm sorry to tell you this...
おっちゃんの奥さんも…。
but your wife died at the time.
おっちゃん？
Mister?
うわ～っ！　うぅ…。
おっちゃん　大丈夫か？
ハァ…　ハァ…　ハァ…。
Mister! Are you all right?
思い出した。
I remember now.
俺は　ヤツに…　うっ！
That guy, he...
封印されたんだ。
ヤツ？
sealed me away.
That guy?
俺は　暗部の命令で→
Under orders from Anbu Black Ops,
里に入り込んだ
スパイの捜索を続けていた。
I was investigating the infiltration
of spies in Hidden Leaf Village.
そこに　疑いが浮上してきたのが
サビルだった。
One man I came to suspect was Sabiru.
サビルは　都市防衛の戦術部門で
木ノ葉の未来を担うと→
Sabiru was an exceptional ninja in
the Tactical Division for Village Defense,
ウワサされていた　優秀な忍だ。
and it was thought that he would
guide the Hidden Leaf to its future.
確たる証拠もないのに
ヤツを糾弾することはできない。
I couldn't accuse him without
solid evidence.
それで俺は
誰にも　そのことを話さずに→
So I continued my investigation
without a word to anyone.
内偵を続けていた。
その最中…。
And then...
((出てこいよ。
Come on out.
俺が気づいてないと
思っているのか？
Or did you think I hadn't noticed?
何か勘づいてるようだが
かくれんぼもここまでだ。
It seems you're on to me,
but this cat-and-mouse game is over.
やはり　貴様！
So it is you!
逃がすか！
You won't get away!
何っ！？
これは！
Wha-?
What is this?!
終わりだ。
クソ！
It's over.
な～んてね。
Damn it.
Fooled you.
うわ～っ！
（サビル）たいしたことねぇな。
You're not that strong.
悪いが　ここに来る直前
お前の妻は始末させてもらった。
I hate to tell you this,
but I got rid of your wife
just before coming here.
なんだと！？
What did you say?!
貴様！
Why you...
ここで　お前の魂を封印すれば→
If I seal your soul here,
やがて　お前の肉体は
水死体で見つかるだろう。
you will probably be found
having drowned.
任務に疲れ　おかしくなったお前は
妻を道連れにし　川に身投げした。
Suffering from the stress
of your assignment,
you threw yourself and
your wife into the river.
一家心中という筋書きだ。
A husband-and-wife suicide.
That's the scenario.
じゃあな！
魂身別離の術！
So long!
Soul Detachment Jutsu.
(うっ…　うわ～っ！))
サビルの目的は→
Sabiru intends to put
his security network into place
自分の立てた防衛網を
木ノ葉にひくことだ。
そうなれば→
in Hidden Leaf Village.
ヤツが　里の守備機能の実権を
握ることになる。
Then he will have control of
the village's defense system.
それだけは
なんとしても阻止しなければ。
Whatever it takes,
he must be stopped.
でも　どうやって…。
But how?
先生　体温が。
血圧が上がりません。
Doctor, his temperature...
ダメです！
His blood pressure isn't going back up!
It's not working.
おっちゃん
どうしたんだってばよ。
Mister, what happened?!
下がって　治療の邪魔だ。
Step back, you're in our way!
おい　いったい
何があったんだよ！
Just what happened here?!
それが　急に
生命維持装置がとまって…。
The life support system suddenly stopped.
心拍　戻りません。
ダメか…。
I'm not getting a heart rate!
It's no use.
そんな…。
No way...
おっちゃん
死んじゃダメだってばよ！
Mister, you can't die!
おっちゃん…。
Mister...
泣くな　ナルト。
おっちゃん。
Don't cry, Naruto!
誰かが装置をとめて
俺を殺したんだ。
Mister!
Someone turned off my life support
and killed me.
犯人は　俺の存在が邪魔なヤツ。
What?
The culprit is someone who
found me to be a threat.
サビルか！
これより　サビルの提案による→
You mean, Sabiru?
And now, we will vote on
木ノ葉防衛網議案の
可決に移ります。
Sabiru's security network measure
for the Hidden Leaf Village.
では
本議案に賛成の者は挙手を。
All those in favor of this plan,
raise your hands!
ふむ。　では　本案は
賛成多数をもって可決…。
By majority vote to adopt this measure-
異議あり！
I oppose!
その決議　待ってください！
Please wait on your decision!
お前は…。
奇介！？
- Who are you?
- Kisuke?
異議というのは
どういうことかね？
What do you mean you oppose?
私は　暗部の奇介という者です。
My name is Kisuke and I belong
to the Anbu Black Ops.
特命を受け
密かにこの里に潜入した→
I was on a secret mission to
investigate a spy
スパイの捜査をしていました。
who had infiltrated our village.
それが　この議決と
何の関係があるのかね？
And what does that have to do
with today's resolution?
おおありだってばよ。
A whole lot, I tell you!
ナルト　興奮するな。
変化の術がバレる。
Naruto, don't get too excited or
they'll see through your Transformation Jutsu.
わかったってばよ。
I know that.
おおありじゃなくて
大いに関係があります。
What I meant was,
it has much to do with it.
なぜなら　私が捜査していたのは
そこにいる　サビルなのですから。
Because the one under investigation
happens to be Sabiru!
なんだと！？
なに！
お待ちください。
- What?
- Impossible!
One moment please!
では　奇介
その証拠は　どこにある？
Well then, Kisuke, where is the proof?!
私は　お前に魂を封印された。
You sealed away my soul!
私自身が証拠だ。
This very body is the proof!
それは　お前が本当の奇介ならな。
That's...if you're the real Kisuke.
奇介は　先ほど死亡したと
報告を受けた。　確認を！
I received a report that
Kisuke died a while earlier.
Verify this!
Yes sir.
クッ…　ここまでか。
クソ！
Is this the end?
Damn it!
《なに！？》
What?
この奇介は　ニセモノだ　捕らえろ！
This Kisuke is an imposter!
Arrest him!
チッ　見失ったか。
I've lost sight of him.
お前は　いったい誰だ？
Just who are you?!
そんな姿で俺の前に
現れるってことは　奇介の仲間か？
Appearing before me like that...
悪いが　お前にも死んでもらうぜ。
Are you helping Kisuke?
That's unfortunate because
you're going to die too.
やっぱり　お前が　おっちゃんと
奥さんを殺したんだな。
So you did kill him
and his wife, after all.
誰だ　小僧。
そうなんだな？
だとしたら？
Who are you, brat?
Isn't that so?
許せねえ。
And if I did?
You won't get away with it!
すべて　ナルトの言うとおりだったな。
You were right about everything, Naruto.
解！
Release!
カカシ。
ま　一応
ソイツは俺の大事な部下なんでね。
Kakashi?!
He happens to be one
of my subordinates.
木ノ葉の防衛網の実権を握り→
You're going to tell us all about
what you planned to do
何をするつもりだったのか
詳しく話してもらうよ。
after taking control of
the Hidden Leaf defense system.
覚悟しろ　サビル。
待ってくれ　カカシ先生！
It's over, Sabiru!
Wait, Kakashi Sensei!
おっちゃん
自分で仇を討つってばよ。
Mister, take your own revenge!
ああ！
（２人）変化の術！
Yeah!
- Transformation Jutsu!
サビル覚悟しろ。　多重影分身の術！
Sabiru! Prepare to die!
Multi Shadow Clone Jutsu!
いくぞ！
Here we go!
サビル　食らえ！
Sabiru!
- Take this!
うわ～っ！
なに？
What?
おい！
Hey!
チッ。
ダメだ　カカシ先生。
No...
《消されたか》
Kakashi Sensei!
He was taken out.
ありがとう　ナルト。
キミのおかげで里は救われたよ。
Thank you, Naruto.
Hidden Leaf Village was saved
because of you.
俺じゃねえ。
I didn't do it.
おっちゃんが取り憑いてくれた
おかげだってばよ。
It was because you possessed me!
そんなことはないさ。
No such thing.
けど　おっちゃん…。
But Mister...
ホントにお化けになっちまって。
Now you're a real ghost.
いいんだよ。　あの世で
妻を見つけて　幸せに暮らすさ。
That's okay.
I'll find my wife in the other world
and live happily ever after.
I have one favor to ask, Naruto.
What is it?
If you ever think about me,
can you place some tulips on our graves?
It was my wife's favorite flower.
Sure thing!
Well, it's time to say goodbye, Naruto.
Live life to the fullest
for our sake too.
Mister!
Yeah, I will, Kisuke!
So long!
mayonaka no utaga sakenda
The poetry of midnight cries out,
boku hontou wa ano hi kara zutto
"Ever since that day, I actually..."
akaku sukitooru yuugure no ato
After the twilight in hues of red,
hoshi tachi wa sora ni tsuwari sorezore no oto kanadeteitta
Stars sit on the sky, Each making their own sound
sunao ni nare to iware nakutemo
You don't need to tell me to be true to myself
namida wa mo boku no omoi tsurete
My tears have already taken my feelings
ashi moto de chiisana umi ni natta
and formed a small ocean at my feet
sora wa ugokanai higa nobori oriru dake
The sky is still. Only the sun rises and sets
jimen wa ugokanai kimi ga arukuka arukanaika dake da
The ground is still. It's up to you to take a step or not
mayonaka no uta ga sakenda
The poetry of midnight cries out,
boku hontou wa hitori ga kirai da
"I actually hate being alone. I hate it"
dai kirai da taisetsu wo shitte shimatta ano hi kara zutto
Since that day I learned what was important
aa shiawase nante chiisana spoon de tsukueru kurai de
A small spoonful of happiness is more than enough
jyuubun nanda wakeaeru hito ga iruka inaika dake da
It's just whether you have someone to share it with or not
ナルト　ひとつ頼みがあるんだが。
Next Episode
What is this?!
Sasuke, what does this mean?
何だってばよ。
もし　俺を
思い出すことがあったら→
How would I know?
俺たちの墓に
チューリップを飾ってくれないか？
Besides, whose fault do you think it is
that we're in this situation?
妻が大好きだったんだ。
You're one to talk!
It's your fault Sakura's been captured!
ああ。
Shut it! While we argue like this,
Sakura's chance of survival only diminishes!
じゃあな　ナルト。　お別れだ。
We can't do anything by ourselves!
俺たちのぶんまで生きろよ。
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "The Worst Three-Legged Race"
The Worst Three-Legged Race
おっちゃん！
ああ　奇介のおっちゃん！
Nothing good comes
about when you're around.
(じゃあな！))